Okay, today's דף daf is דף ד, Daf Dalet, בבא קמא. Bava
Kamma. We're in a new מסכת, masechet, and we pick up in
the bottom of ג עמוד ב. Gimmel Amud Bet. And our learning
today should be in the זכות zechut of the חיילים chayalim and
חיילות chayolot that God should protect them and ensure that they're safe
and the return, speedy return of all of our captives and a
speedy end to all of the horror that we're in right now.
So we pick up in the middle of ג עמוד ב Gimmel
Amud Bet and we have just said that the idea of תולדותיהן
לאו כיוצא בהן toldoteihen lav keyotzei bahen that רב פפא Rav Pappa
said on the משנה mishna about the אבות נזיקין avot nezikin applies
to רגל, regel, applies to an animal that's walking and we're talking
about חצי נזק צרורות. chatzi nezek tzerorot. So let's pick up with
that and then we'll go back and sort of summarize what we've
really been saying until now because really the opening, these opening two
דף daf have been an introduction to ארבעה אבות נזיקין, Arba Avot
Nezikin, but through the question that רב פפא Rav Pappa or through
the question that the גמרא Gemara asked about whether the תולדות toldot
are כיוצא בהן, kyotze bahen, are the derivatives of the אב av
like them or not like them, and רב פפא Rav Pappa said,
you know, that there are those that are like them and those
not like them and we've identified that the one case where the
תולדה tolda is not like it is the חצי נזק צרורות. chatzi
nezek tzerorot. So let's pick up with that.
וכי קאמר Ve-chi kamar רב פפא Rav Pappa תולדה דרגל. tolda de-regel.
So this is right across from the תוספות לפוטרו, Tosafot le-potro, it's
about exactly a little more than halfway down on ג עמוד ב.
Gimmel Amud Bet. When did רב פפא Rav Pappa say that תולדותיהם
toldoteihem were לאו כיוצא בהן, lav keyotzei bahen, that there were some
תולדות toldot that were not like the אב? av? That was the
תולדה tolda of רגל. regel. רגל, Regel, says the גמרא, Gemara, הא
אוקימנא ha okiman תולדה דרגל כרגל. tolda de-regel ke-regel. We said that
we, you know, had discussions what are the תולדה tolda of רגל,
regel, whether it's walking on something that's the אב av of רגל
regel or whether it's hitting something with its body as it's walking
or with its tail, and all of that was the same basic
characteristic that it, it, you know, that it did something, it was
not כוונתו להזיק kavanato lehazik and it did it דרך הלוכו derech
hilucho as it was walking and you paid full נזק. nezek. So
where is it לאו כיוצא בהן? lav keyotzei bahen? So the גמרא
Gemara says בחצי נזק צרורות דהלכתא גמירי לה. be-chatzi nezek tzerorot de-hilkhata
gemiri lah. It's talking about that you only pay half damages when
it's through the pebbles that it's kicking as it's walking and that
is a tradition. הלכתא גמירי לה Hilkhata gemiri lah which is generally
understood to be הלכה למשה מסיני, Halakha Le-Moshe Mi-Sinai, okay, that you
only pay half. So that's its רגל regel because as the animal
is walking it is, and not intending to do damage, incidental to
its walking it's destroying, but it's not destroying with its body or
things attached to its body, it's destroying with its כוח koach where
with something that was propelled because of the animal by the stones
that were kicked up and it was also its incidental כוח koach
which makes it less connected to the animal. So the הלכה למשה
מסיני Halakha Le-Moshe Mi-Sinai about this is called חצי נזק צרורות chatzi
nezek tzerorot is that on the one hand it is like רגל
regel because it's part of the animal's walking, on the other hand,
not only is it not physically the animal, it's not so connected
to the animal, it happened as something that it propelled incidentally, it's
like what we would call if it was a human being מתעסק.
mitasek. So how much are the pebbles really connected to the animal
all together? So because of that less direct connection, it's only paying
half damage. ואמאי קרי ליה Ve-amai kari lei תולדה דרגל? tolda de-regel?
So why is it called תולדה דרגל? tolda de-regel? Now obviously it's
תולדה דרגל tolda de-regel because that's the way it's damaging, but תוספות
Tosafot says why doesn't it, you know, but the גמרא Gemara is
also maybe asking why doesn't it have a name for itself or
also in what way is the הלכה halakha similar, you know, to
that of a רגל? regel? לשלומי מן העליה. Le-shalemi min ha-aliya. That
it is not like another type of half damage, a classic half
damage is that of a קרן keren of an ox that is
goring כוונתו להזיק kavanato lehazik that pays half damages, but that the
payment is only coming from the body of the animal itself. That's,
you know, מגופו. mi-gufo. This is that it pays from עליה aliya
from the best of property, meaning that you, although you're only paying
half damages, you are paying it out of pocket not from the
body of the מזיק. mazik. So in that way it is similar
to רגל. regel. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says והא מיבעיא בעי
רבא, ve-ha mibaya be-aya Rava, but רבא Rava asked that question. דבעי
רבא, Debaya Rava, רבא Rava asked: חצי נזק צרורות מגופו משלם או
מן העליה משלם? Chatzi nezek tzerorot mi-gufo meshalem o min ha-aliya meshalem?
Because you're paying half by קרן, keren, maybe it should be like
קרן keren that it only comes from the body of the animal.
So according to רבא, Rava, it maybe it's very similar to קרן.
keren. You pay half and it's from the body of the animal.
In what way is it similar to רגל? regel? So the גמרא
Gemara says לרבא דמיבעיא ליה לרב פפא פשיטא ליה. le-Rava de-mibaya lei
le-Rav Pappa peshita lei. Yeah, you're right. רבא Rava is not certain
about that, רב פפא Rav Pappa is. So for רב פפא Rav
Pappa it's clear that it's a תולדה דרגל tolda de-regel because even
though it's half, it's still very much anchored in the payment of
רגל regel that you pay from the עליה aliya not from the
body of the animal and also the damage is a רגל regel
type of a damage. So the
גמרא Gemara says לרבא דמיבעיא ליה אמאי קרי ליה תולדה דרגל? le-Rava
de-mibaya lei amai kari lei tolda de-regel? Meaning if you have both
that it's half and it might actually come from the animal itself,
from the body of the animal, the value of the animal itself
and if the animal itself is not worth half the damages then
the damaged party is is out being fully compensated or half compensated,
right, that's the idea of מגופו. mi-gufo. So according to רבא Rava
if it has those two qualities... If it has those two qualities
that are like קרן, keren, number one it's only half, and b,
it's not directly out of the bank account of the מזיק mazik
but only from the body of the animal, so those two are
very much like קרן, keren, so why is it being called רגל?
regel? Or, as I might say, in what halakhic way is it
like רגל, regel, even though that's the way that it damaged was
a רגל regel type of damage? So the גמרא Gemara says לפטור
ברשות הרבים, Liphtor bir'shus harabbim, to tell you that you're exempt in
רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, because this is one of the major differences
between רגל regel and קרן. keren. קרן, keren, where the animal is
intentionally damaging, it doesn't matter if it does it in the public
domain because, you know, it's not, that's a fundamentally unacceptable to be
doing an act of intentional damage in the public domain, and an
owner has a responsibility to make sure his animal does not do
that. So whether the my animal gores yours in the public domain
or goes into your property and gores yours, I'm חייב. chayav. קרן
keren is חייב chayav everywhere, whereas רגל, regel, שן ורגל shen ve'regel
actually, because it would be impossible, it would be an undue burden
to say that as I'm walking with my animal in the public
domain, it's my responsibility to make sure it doesn't bump into anything
or eat from some, you know, fruit that's in the middle of
the road, right? Because since that's just a normal way the animal
is acting, that would be seen as an undue responsibility. So actually,
in order to make life livable, we have to allow that the
owners are not responsible in the public domain for שן ורגל, shen
ve'regel, but actually, you know, the damaged party just has to accept
that loss. Another way of, and they have to be the one
that are responsible to make sure, they have to protect their stuff
to make sure that all of the animals that are walking back
and forth aren't bumping into their things. That's for them to watch
out, not the owners of the animal. Another way of framing this,
which is really two sides of a coin, is to say that
that's a case of פשיעת הניזק, pshia'as hanizak, of the negligence of
the one that is damaged. Since there are so many animals walking
in רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, if you, if my animal goes ahead
and bumps into your thing, that's your, your negligence that you let
it happen. That's not my negligence, it's your negligence. Now of course
whose negligence it is is really a function of who has the
duty to watch. Do I have the duty to watch my animal,
do you have the duty to watch your objects? So those are
really like two sides of the same coin. But either way, שן
ורגל shen ve'regel is exempt in רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, and here
we are saying that the same is true by חצי נזק צרורות.
chatzi nezek tzaroros. So not only is the damaging the way of
רגל, regel, that it's through natural walking, not כוונתו להזיק, kavanaso lehazik,
etc.,
but
even if the payment is half and it's from the body, fundamentally
it is still רגל regel because it is exempt in רשות הרבים,
reshus harabbim, which follows the logic of רגל. regel. תוספות Tosafos also
points out that the reason we know that that's true, you know,
even once we said half which could be pulling us to the
קרן keren category, is that we are being more lenient by חצי
נזק צרורות. chatzi nezek tzaroros. So we obviously, right, you're not paying
full, you're only paying half, so obviously we're not going to be
stricter on you and make you liable in רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim.
The whole idea of half is making it more lenient, so the
exemption of רשות הרבים reshus harabbim still applies to חצי נזק צרורות.
chatzi nezek tzaroros. Fine. So with that we have concluded that there
is one example of תולדותיהן לאו כיוצא בהן, toladoseyn lo ke'yotzei bahen,
which is this case of a רגל regel walking, indirectly kicking up
stones, breaking something, and that is like רגל regel because it's the
way it's damaged, it's a תולדה toldah of רגל, regel, it's exempt
in רשות הרבים reshus harabbim like רגל, regel, but it's not כיוצא
בהן ke'yotzei bahen that you only pay half. Now, before we continue,
what we should point out is that what the גמרא Gemara did
in this opening סוגיא, sugya, and this sometimes happens in opening סוגיות,
sugyos, these are often understood as סבראי, sevaraik, where the, it introduced
a question which was not necessarily the most pressing of questions: תולדותיהן
כיוצא בהן או לאו כיוצא בהן, toladoseyn ke'yotzei bahen or lo ke'yotzei
bahen, whether the תולדות toldos are like them or not like them.
I mean, we would obviously assume they were, and as we see,
we really, you stretch to find one that wasn't. And as a
result of that question, it allowed us, gave us the excuse to
give a certain survey of everything we're going to be seeing. And
in the last two דף daf what we've done is that we've
introduced, we've, you know, all of the תורה Torah sources for the
categories for the אבות נזיקין, avos nezikin, and we've discussed what their
conceptual logic is. We haven't exactly, until we got here to discussing
half or full or רשות הרבים reshus harabbim or not, we haven't
discussed fully what their דינים dinim are, but we've described what their
conceptual category is. So the משנה Mishnah opened with שור, shor, right?
So שור shor we discussed קרן, שן ורגל, keren shen ve-regel the
three parts of שור, shor, and we discussed the פסוקים psukim that
they were all based on, you know, where קרן keren, is explicit,
שן ורגל, shen ve'regel, ושלח את בעירו וביער veshilach es be'iro u'vi'er
and so on. And we said that conceptually, that was not exactly
which part of the body it's using, but conceptually קרן keren is
כוונתו להזיק, kavanaso lehazik, רגל regel is, you
know,
is that it's what the גמרא Gemara calls היזיקו מצוי, hezeiko matzui,
it's, you know, the damage is prevalent because it's sort of, but
what it really is is sort of like דרך הילוכה derech hillucho
would be maybe a more exact precise way to say what רגל
regel is, something that is likely to damage or it's as it's
just in its normal act of... of walking and its אין כוונתו
להזיק. ein kavanaso l'hazik. שן Shen is הנאה להזיקו, hana'ah l'hezeiko, that
it gets benefit directly through the damage that it is doing, so
its כוונה kavana is the not להזיק l'hazik but its כוונה kavana
is for its own הנאה. hana'ah. So those are the those conceptual
three categories. And and then we discussed cases where it would not
be, you know, using the tooth or using the leg etc. or
using the horn, but it's conceptually about כוונתו להזיק, kavanaso l'hazik, היזק
מצוי hezek matzuy slash דרך הילוכה, derech hilucha, or or הנאה להזיקו.
hana'ah l'hezeiko. Interesting question what happens if it has multiple of those,
well we'll bracket that for now. Then that's so השור. ha'shor. Then
we discussed הבור. ha'bor. You know בור Bor was what the גמרא
Gemara calls תחילת עשייתו לנזק. techilas asiyaso l'nezek. From its very beginning
it was a something, it was a danger, it was something that
could cause damage, it was a hazard. Okay, so that's like a
בור, Bor, that's a very weighty idea that it could cause hazard.
We also discussed a בור Bor for מיתה misa and a בור
Bor for נזק, nezek, two types of בור, Bor, right? So that's
שור, Shor, בור, Bor, מבעה. Mav'eh. מבעה Mav'eh we discussed either that
was, you know, שן Shen or it which we'll see it discussed
in a minute or it's אדם. Adam. אדם Adam we didn't really
elaborate on but אדם Adam is מועד לעולם. muad l'olam. And then
we did הבער He'ver and then we did אש, Esh, right? And
אש Esh was and what the גמרא Gemara says כח אחר מעורב
בו, koach acher m'urav bo, that another energy was mixed up into
it, also something that damages like דרך הילוכה derech hilucha as it's
spreading. And that is the conceptual category of אש. Esh. So we
have now defined the sources of these פסוקים psukim and their conceptual
definitions and understanding. The other thing that is worth saying before we
continue on is when the גמרא Gemara said, you know, the תולדות
Toldos should be כיוצא בהן k'yozei bahen and it went back to
the line in the משנה Mishna about why you should be חייב,
chayav, the repeating line in the גמרא Gemara all the time was,
you know, וממונך ושמירתן עליך. u'mamoncha u'shmirasan alecha. It says, you know,
קרן keren is כוונתו להזיק וממונך ושמירתן עליך. kavanaso l'hazik u'mamoncha u'shmirasan
alecha. אש Esh is כח אחר מעורב בו וממונך ושמירתן עליך. koach
acher m'urav bo u'mamoncha u'shmirasan alecha. So that idea that we're dealing
that the fundamental conceptual idea of why you're חייב chayav when your
property damages, you know, which is the צד השווה tzad ha'shaveh of
the משנה, Mishna, the משנה Mishna said, you know, that the הצד
השווה שבהן ha'tzad ha'shaveh she'bahen our משנה Mishna says
is, הצד השווה שבהן שדרכן להזיק ושמירתן עליך. ha'tzad ha'shaveh she'bahen she'darkan
l'hazik u'shmirasan alecha. But when the גמרא Gemara summarized it, it's, you
know, it replaced דרכן להזיק darkan l'hazik with the specific characteristic of
each one, כוונתו להזיק, kavanaso l'hazik, הנאה להזיקו, hana'ah l'hezeiko, being more
specific, that was the unique what was unique to each category. But
it didn't but then it didn't just say שמירתן עליך, shmirasan alecha,
it also said וממונך. u'mamoncha. It's your property. But the question is,
is this really all about being your property? You know, is בור
Bor if you dig it in a public domain, is that about
it being your property? Is a fire about it being your property?
And the answer is maybe, right? And that's going to be a
central question that we're going to be dealing with. How much is
the obligation of the אבות נזיקין Avos Nezikin because it's your property
that did damage? And then we're going to have to conceptualize a
fire that you made is like you own it, even if, you
know, it was some I don't know a fire that you lit
somebody else's fire on somebody else's thing, still if you're the one
causing its spread, it's like it's your fire, conceptually it's your property.
A בור Bor that you dug, a pit that you dug is
like you own it. Is there a conceptual idea of it being
your property, is that central to the obligation? And the fact that
the גמרא Gemara we have consistently repeated the word וממונך, u'mamoncha, which
could reflect the idea that that was its גירסא girsa in the
משנה, Mishna, וממונך, mamoncha, that gets to that important question. תוספות Tosafot
along the way raises whether we should have the גירסא girsa וממונך
mamoncha or not. Okay, so that's what we've done so far. We've
introduced all the אבות נזיקין, Avos Nezikin, what are their פסוקים, psukim,
what are their conceptual definition? And we've also
interestingly used the word וממונך u'mamoncha which indicates that that might have
been in the משנה Mishna and that that might be also central
to the idea of why you're חייב. chayav. Now we go to
look at the משנה Mishna about these phrase מבעה. Mav'eh. מבעה Mav'eh
and הבער, He'ver, הבער He'ver we know is fire but what is
this מבעה Mav'eh that mysterious phrase in the
משנה? Mishna? המבעה וההבער. Ha'mav'eh v'ha'he'ver. So we're now about twenty lines
from the bottom on גמל עמוד ב. Gimmel amud beis. מאי מבעה?
Mai mav'eh? What is מבעה? mav'eh? רב אמר מבעה זה אדם. Rav
amar mav'eh zeh adam. It's a person, right? That was missing from
the משנה. Mishna. ושמואל אמר מבעה זה השן. u'Shmuel amar mav'eh zeh
ha'shen. It is the
tooth. Okay? רב אמר מבעה זה אדם דכתיב אמר שומר אתא בוקר
וגם לילה אם תבעיון בעיו. Rav amar mav'eh zeh adam d'ksiv amar
shomer asa boker v'gam layla im tivayun b'ayu. Which is, you know,
the watchman says the morning has come and even the לילה, layla,
if you will inquire inquire. So that refers to a human being
that inquires. So that's, you know, that's a very human
quality. ושמואל אמר מבעה זה השן. u'Shmuel amar mav'eh zeh ha'shen. ומבעה
Mav'eh means the
tooth. דכתיב איך נחפשו עשיו נבעו מצפוניו. D'ksiv eich nichpesu Eisav niv'u
mitzpunav. How has עשיו Eisav been searched out, how has his hidden
places been revealed? So somehow that the that the tooth is something
that is, you know, when your mouth is open or whatever, sometimes
revealed, sometimes covered. מאי משמע? Mai mashma? Where do you get that
from the פסוק? pasuk? כדמתרגם רב יוסף. K'demisargem Rav Yosef. רב יוסף
Rav Yosef would provide the Aramaic
translation. איכדין אישתבלש עשו. Ech dein isablish Eisav. How has Esav been
searched out, אתגלין מטמרוהי, itgalin matmurohi, his hidden places been revealed. Okay.
ורב מאי טעמא לא אמר כשמואל? veRav mai ta’ama lo amar keShmuel?
Now why did Rav not say like say not say like Shmuel?
אמר לך מי קתני נבע? amar lach mi katani niv’eh? So first
we're just going to focus on the whether the what the word
you know grammatically suggests. If it was about the tooth it should
have said נבע, niv’eh, the thing that is revealed. מבעה mav’eh means
the thing that does the revealing. ושמואל מאי טעמא לא אמר כרב?
veShmuel mai ta’ama lo amar keRav? Why did Shmuel not like say
like Rav? אמר לך מי קתני בועה? amar lach mi katani bo’eh?
It cannot say בועה bo’eh which means to inquire, it says מבעה.
mav’eh. So מכדי. michdi. So now the גמרא Gemara says fine. Look,
I mean מבעה mav’eh is a hard fit to either of these
פסוקים. pesukim. מכדי קרא לא כמר דייק ולא כמר דייק, michdi kra
lo kemar dayek velo kemar dayek, the פסוק pasuk doesn't really fit
well either explanation or it doesn't sort of come down decisively on
one. רב מאי טעמא לא אמר כשמואל? Rav mai ta’ama lo amar
keShmuel? Let's get back to the real reason why Rav did not
say like Shmuel. Why not read the פסוק pasuk to talk about
a tooth? Not the פסוק, pasuk, the משנה. mishnah. תנא שור וכל
מילי דשור. tana shor vechol milei de-shor. Because once it says שור,
shor, right, that's all-inclusive and that's sort of how the גמרא Gemara
structured itself. It started with
קרן שן ורגל keren shen ve-regel? to going through the משנה mishnah
of שור. shor. So שור shor includes all the types of damages
of שור, shor, מבעה mav’eh must be something
else. ושמואל נמי התנא ליה שור. veShmuel nami hatana lei shor. So
Shmuel doesn't it say שור? shor? Doesn't that include
קרן Keren שן ורגל? shen ve'regel, אמר רב יהודה אמר רב יהודה.
amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav Yehuda. רב יהודה Rav Yehuda said תנא
שור לקרנו מבעה לשינו. tana shor lekarno mav’eh leshino. No, Shmuel understood
that שור shor like the paradigmatic ox, when you think about the
ox you know there's so many cases in the תורה Torah about
an ox, you're thinking about an ox goring. I mean actually שן
ורגל shen ve-regel are very you know not explicit in the פסוקים.
pesukim. So שור shor means קרן. keren. And and therefore what you're
left with מבעה mav’eh to mean is שן. shen. All right. והכי
קאמר. vehachi ka’amar. And this is how to read it. Now that
will be great you know if we think that it means שן
ורגל shen ve-regel because שן ורגל shen ve-regel are pretty similar they're
learned from the same פסוק. pasuk. They're פטור patur in רשות הרבים.
reshut ha-rabim. They're the natural act of the animal. So but we'll
have we'll see in a minute that Shmuel you know whether we
can read it as being שן ורגל shen ve-regel or just שן.
shen. But for now שור shor is קרן keren and מבעה mav’eh
is
שן. shen. והכי קאמר. vehachi ka’amar. Now here's how you read the
משנה mishnah right because the משנה mishnah remember compares שור shor and
מבעה mav’eh and says they're not similar to one another but they
have the common denominator that they're רוח חיים ruach chayim alive thing.
So that works for Rav you know an animal and an ox
are not similar but they're both alive and it works for Shmuel
a goring and a שן shen are are not exactly similar but
they're both alive animal. But now we're going to just drill down
and explain in what ways are what is the strength of one
and the strength of the other in terms of קרן keren versus
שן shen for
Shmuel.
והכי קאמר. vehachi ka’amar. Here's how you read the משנה. mishnah. לא
ראי קרן שאין הנאה להיזקו כראי שן שיש הנאה להיזקו. lo re’i
keren she’ein hana’ah lehizko kere’i shen sheyesh hana’ah lehizko. The characteristic of
קרן keren that you're חייב chayav is is not similar to that
of שן shen because קרן keren does you don't have benefit from
you know it's not deriving benefit when it gores. So that's why
it's חייב chayav and that's not similar to שן shen that is
deriving benefit. Now we'll see in a minute ולא ראי שן velo
re’i shen and top of דף ד עמוד א, daf daled amud
aleph, the characteristic of שן שאין כוונתו להזיק shen she’ein kavanato lehazik.
isn't intending to damage that's not כראי קרן שכוונתו להזיק kere’i keren
shekavanato lehazik is not like קרן keren that is intending to damage.
Now the funny thing with this is which the גמרא Gemara is
about is exactly asks is that when we say לא ראי זה
כראי זה lo re’i zeh kere’i zeh and this quality is X
we're saying this is the reason why it's חייב chayav and therefore
you might not be חייב chayav in the other case. So the
גמרא Gemara got it reversed. It should have said that ראי קרן
re’i keren is כוונתו להזיק kavanato lehazik and that's why you're חייב
chayav and therefore you could not necessarily have assumed שן shen that
isn't intending to damage. And then the reverse. ראי השן re’i hashen
that is
חייב chayav
is because
there's הנאה להיזקו hana’ah lehizko and that's now and that's why you're
חייב chayav because it gets benefit and that's not like קרן keren
that there's not הנאה להיזקו. hana’ah lehizko. So you know the idea
of comparing them and pointing out these differences of get whether one
has benefit and one is intending to damage makes a lot of
sense, but the גמרא Gemara got reversed the way it should have
said it. Which is what the גמרא Gemara right now challenges. So
the גמרא Gemara says ולאו קל וחומר הוא? velav kal va-chomer hu?
The גמרא Gemara says wait a minute the you know it's a
קל וחומר kal va-chomer that you should be חייב chayav based on
the way you framed
it. ומה שן שאין כוונתו להזיק חייב, u-mah shen she’ein kavanato lehazik
chayav, if you're going to say oh
שן shen שאין כוונתו להזיק. she’ein kavanato lehazik Well if that's if
you're חייב chayav even if אין כוונתו להזיק ein kavanato lehazik if
you're starting with that quality of שן shen even though it's not
intending to damage קרן שכוונתו להזיק לא כל שכן? keren shekavanato lehazik
lo kol she-ken? Certainly you should be חייב chayav by קרן keren
that you are intending to damage. So basically the גמרא Gemara says
yes you got the points correct one is כוונתו להזיק kavanato lehazik
and one is הנאה להיזקו hana’ah lehizko but you said it in
the reverse way. You should you know what do you mean oh
well if you're חייב chayav by שן shen that's not כוונתו להזיק
kavanato lehazik you don't know that you'd be חייב chayav by קרן
keren that is כוונתו להזיק. kavanato lehazik. Of course you should be
חייב chayav by קרן keren that's כוונתו להזיק. kavanato lehazik. So the
גמרא Gemara is not yet ready to reverse itself, it will reverse
itself in a minute but first it tries to defend. this position.
So the גמרא Gemara says no, אצטריך. itztarich. No, no, no, I
would not have assumed even though you're חייב chayav by שן, shein,
which is לאו כוונתו להזיק, lav kavanaso lehazik, I would have thought
maybe by קרן keren that's כוונתו להזיק kavanaso lehazik you actually would
be
פטור. patur. Why? אצטריך סלקא דעתך אמינא מידי דהוי עבד ואמה, itztarich
salka deitach amina midei dehavei aved v'amah, like what happens when your
servants go out and damage. Okay, that when your servants go out
and damage, you actually as the owner are פטור, patur, even if
they're willfully
damaging. עבד ואמה לאו אף על גב דכוונתן להזיק אפילו הכי פטירי.
aved v'amah lav af al gav dekavanasan lehazik afilu hachi paturi. By
your servants even although they damage, even nevertheless you're still פטור, patur,
and we'll see why in a minute. So therefore when somebody something
is intentionally damaging, maybe it's a reason to be פטור. patur. So
actually you could have said it that way. שן, shein, you're חייב
chayav because it's not intentionally damaging. I wouldn't have known that you
would be חייב chayav by קרן, keren, which is intentionally damaging. הכא
נמי לא שנא, hacha nami lo shana, and that's why, that's the
לא ראיה lo rei'ei of the משנה. Mishnah. The משנה Mishnah had
to say, the תורה Torah had to say both שן shein and
קרן, keren, just because you're חייב chayav by שן shein doesn't mean
you're חייב chayav by קרן. keren. Right now the way we're reading
it is that קרן keren actually maybe you would be פטור patur
because it's intentionally damaging. Okay now, let's try to understand what the
logic is by the servants and see if that's relevant, the slaves
and see if that's relevant by the קרן. keren. So the גמרא
Gemara says: אמר רב אשי אטו עבד ואמה לאו טעמא רבה אית
בהו amar Rav Ashi atu aved v'amah lav taama rabba it behu?
רב אשי Rav Ashi says wait a minute, wait a minute, wait
a minute. By the case of the servants why you're פטור, patur,
isn't there a really, really good reason that they're פטור patur there
and it's not relevant to קרן? keren? What's the good reason you're
פטור patur there? שמא יקניטנו רבו וילך וידליק גדישו של חברו ונמצא
זה מחייב את רבו מאה מנה בכל יום. shemma yaknitenu rabbo v'yeilech
v'yadlik gedisho shel chaveiro v'nimtza zeh mechayeves rabbo me'ah maneh bechol yom.
It's a משנה. Mishnah. It's a משנה Mishnah that says that you're
פטור patur when your slaves damage.
Says
the reason you're פטור patur is because if you'd be חייב, chayav,
then when their master got, you know, their owner made them really
angry at them, they would go ahead and destroy, you know, burn
up down somebody's house and force their master to be liable and
pay. So therefore we had to פטור patur their master in that
case. And that's why you're פטור. patur. So the reason the master's
פטור patur when his slaves damage actually is, you know, it was
a necessary ruling to פטור patur the master, but it's unique to
the slaves that have real will and you know, and intention, not
just intention to damage, but real like will, and they might be
doing this, you know, in order to get back at their master.
But it's generally not a reason to be פטור. patur. Generally if
קרן keren is כוונתו להזיק, kavanaso lehazik, you should be all the
more so you should be חייב. chayav. So, אלא פרכי הכי. ella
parchi hachi. So the גמרא Gemara says fine, fine, you're right, you're
right, you're right. We got, we did it in the reverse. Here's
how it should read. לא ראיה קרן שכוונתו להזיק כראיה שן שאין
כוונתו להזיק. lo rei'ei keren shekavanaso lehazik kerei'ei shein she'ein kavanaso lehazik.
Reverse what we said before. You start with the strong point, not
the weak point. The power of the קרן keren is כוונתו להזיק,
kavanaso lehazik, and that's maybe why you're חייב chayav and therefore I
could not have assumed שן, shein, which is אין כוונתו להזיק. ein
kavanaso lehazik. ולא ראיה שן שיש הנאה להיזקו כראיה קרן שאין הנאה
להיזקו. v'lo rei'ei shein sheyesh hana'ah lehazzeko kerei'ei keren she'ein hana'ah lehazzeko.
And there, but and the same in the reverse. If the תורה
Torah just said שן, shein, that's because it's getting benefit, and I
would not necessarily
have learned קרן keren that's not getting benefit. And that's why the
תורה Torah had to say both. So that's
the לא ראיה השור כראיה המבעה ולא ראיה המבעה כראיה השור lo
rei'ei hashor kerei'ei hamaveh v'lo rei'ei hamaveh kerei'ei hashor and because each
one of them has a strong point, and they're, you know, and
הצד השווה שבהן hatzad hashaveh shebehen is דהן רוח חיים. d'hein ruach
chayim. And then that's how the משנה Mishnah proceeds. So that's how
you would read the משנה Mishnah like שמואל. Shmuel. It's talking about
שן shein and קרן keren and each one has a strong point
and that you could, and therefore you needed both. Now it's interesting,
it's not exploring how to read the משנה Mishnah like רב, Rav,
you know, what would be the strong point of שור shor as
opposed to אדם המזיק. adam hamazik. If a person is doing it
themselves, you know, although it could be that אדם adam maybe is
חייב chayav even in a case of אונס, onnes, even when he's
unaware and so on, but the גמרא Gemara is not exploring the
reading for רב. Rav. For the reading for שמואל, Shmuel, that's how
you read the משנה. Mishnah. Now before we go on to, now
the גמרא Gemara is about now to ask, now we've read the
משנה Mishnah according to רב, Rav, it's, you know, מבעה maveh is
אדם, adam, it's just אדם adam and then all the part and
שור shor which includes שן, shein, קרן, keren, and רגל. regal. Or
according to שמואל, Shmuel, שור shor is קרן, keren, that's paradigmatic שור
shor and מבעה maveh is שן shein and we're going to discuss
in a minute what happened to רגל. regal. It's worth though pausing
to say two points. One is that the idea of שמא יקניטנו
רבו, shemma yaknitenu rabbo, the way we've read it, it's sort of
like a, you know, a necessary way for the structure of society
we have to go ahead and give the master a pass when
his servants damage. Of course, you know, that could be a problem
the other way, that the master could be irresponsible and so on.
But it could be read differently. It could be read that it's
getting deeper down into this כוונתו להזיק kavanaso lehazik and really more
of a question of will and which is saying that there's no
way, you know, when you're dealing with human beings, every, human beings
are responsible for themselves. You can't be make another human being responsible
for the acts, you know, master responsible for the acts of their
slave because the slaves are people and humans unto themselves and therefore
they're the ones that are primarily responsible for their act and you
cannot shift that responsibility to the master. So that's one way of
understanding what it means שמא יקניטנו רבו. shemma yaknitenu rabbo. That's a,
that's just one point. The other point that's really worth mentioning is
that תוספות Tosafos tries to defend the גמרא'ס Gemara's הוה אמינא havamina
of saying that maybe you'd be more חייב chayav by a שן
shein that is not כוונתו להזיק. kavanaso lehazik. Not for the reason
of the גמרא, Gemara, but because if it's not כוונתו להזיק, kavanaso
lehazik, then it's not such a risk and it's easier to watch,
and therefore if it goes out and damages, you know, you're more
פושע, poshea, you're more negligent. So even though the animal is doing
less of a, you know, of a like a what we would
call an intentionally damaging act looked from the perspective of the animal,
from the perspective of the owner maybe there's more liability because there's
greater responsibility on the owner, you know, because it's so easy to
watch and if you're not watching then there's more negligence. The reason
I bring this up is because this gets us, you know, to
a core question of how you conceptualize the responsibility of ממון המזיק.
mamon hamazik. How much is it that you focus on the act
being done by the animal, you know, or by the fire, by
the whatever? Obviously negligence is a requirement, but fundamentally we start with
the fact that this, you know, animal gored, right? So this was
a damaging act. In that perspective כוונתו להזיק kavanaso lehazik makes it
worse, right? Or do we focus primarily on you're liable because you
were negligent, and who cares how bad the animal was? It's about
your negligence that led to the damage, this is just an animal,
and therefore maybe כוונתו להזיק kavanaso lehazik maybe your negligence is less.
So very interesting to think about are we focusing on the on
the act of damage and the אש esh and the שור shor
and the קרן keren and the שן shein and all of that,
which the גמרא Gemara seems to be, or where does the focus
and the you know of negligence and how central is that? You
know, that's the important question that תוספות Tosafos asks. Okay, now we
continue in the גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא Gemara says ורגל מאי שיירי?
veregel mai shirei? So what happened to רגל? regel? You have קרן
keren and שן shein according to שמואל, Shmuel, that's a very nice
read of the משנה, Mishnah, but what what are you doing with
רגל, regel, you're leaving it off? So the גמרא Gemara says
כשהזיק חב המזיק לאתויי רגל. k'shehizik chav hamazik l'asuyei regel. No, there's
another another משנה Mishnah that's gonna say a rule of כשהזיק חב
המזיק, k'shehizik chav hamazik, which the גמרא'ס Gemara's gonna say, you know,
when it damages, the מזיק mazik is חייב, chayav, comes to include
רגל. regel. So the גמרא Gemara says okay, so we did get
it, but
לאתויי רגל ולתני בהדיא, l'asuyei regel u'lisney b'hedya, but why not put
it in the first משנה, Mishnah, which is the core אבות נזיקין?
avos nezikin? Now this is really a shame, based on this the
גמרא'ס Gemara's gonna reject this read, which is such a beautiful read,
to think that שור shor represents קרן keren and מבעה maveh represents,
you know, שן. shein. The גמרא Gemara now because of this question
where is רגל regel is gonna reject that and say שור shor
is רגל regel and מבעה maveh is שן. shein. The, you know,
because it could have kept this read and just said שן shein
and רגל regel are essentially the same, they learn from the same
פסוק, pasuk, they have all the same הלכות, halachos, שן shein and
רגל regel are always treated exactly the same, but the גמרא Gemara
doesn't do that, because of this question of what happened to רגל
regel we're now going to have a different read of the משנה
Mishnah according to שמואל. Shmuel. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this, where was it? אלא אמר רבא ella amar Rava rather רבא
Rava said תנא שור לרגלו ומבעה לשנו. tana shor l'raglo u'maveh l'shino.
Fine. Take קרן keren out. We're bothered where what happened to רגל,
regel, so שור shor now doesn't mean
קרן, keren, שור shor means רגל, regel, excuse me, which makes a
certain amount of sense, you know, if you think about an ox
like just means the normal movement of an ox is its רגל.
regel. So ומבעה u'maveh is שן shein based on the פסוק. pasuk.
So now we have רגל regel and שן shein in the משנה
Mishnah and we're dropping
קרן. keren. והכי קאמר v'hachi ka'amar and now we have to explain
what the strength of each one is. לא ראי רגל שהזיקה ומצקה
ראי שן שהזיקה ומצקה. lo rei regel she-chazika u-matzaka rei sheen she-chazika
u-matzaka.
רגל'ס Regel's strength that it is very prevalent, the propensity to damage,
it's just as it's walking, that makes sense that you're חייב. chayav.
You could not have learned out שן shein that does not have
that degree of
propensity. ולא ראי השן שיש הנאה להזיקו v'lo rei ha-shein sheyesh hana'ah
lehizeko and the quality of שן shein that it gets benefit when
it eats, is which is more of a reason to be חייב,
chayav, it's more directly connected to the damage and responsible for the
damage, we could see that
in intentional, כראי הרגל שאין הנאה להזיקו. k'rei ha-regel she-ein hana'ah lehizeko.
So if you had one you couldn't have learned out the other,
each one has a strength, רגל regel is the propensity, שן shein
is the הנאה, hana'ah, the benefit, and therefore the תורה Torah had
to say both and that's the לא ראי זה כראי זה lo
rei zeh k'rei zeh of the משנה. Mishnah. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara says וקרן מאי שיירי? v'keren mai shirei? So now we're
back to the question, so what happened to
קרן? keren? כשהזיק חב המזיק לאתויי קרן. k'shehizik chav hamazik l'asuyei keren.
Now we're like we said before, the next משנה Mishnah that says
oh when the thing damages it's חייב, chayav, that's a general rule,
that includes קרן. keren. But now we have an answer why קרן
keren wasn't included in the main
משנה. Mishnah. ולתני בהדיא, v'lisney b'hedya, why not say קרן keren explicitly
in the first
משנה? Mishnah? במועדין מתחילתן קא מיירי בתמין ולבסוף מועדין לא קא מיירי.
b'muadim mitichilasan ka'mari b'tamim u'lisof muadim lo ka'mari. Ah, so we are
dealing with things that are מועד muad from the very outset that
you pay full amount. קרן keren as we know, which is intentional
damage, you only pay half amount from the beginning. So now for
the way שמואל Shmuel has read by cutting out קרן, keren, making
שור shor meaning רגל, regel, we have that the first משנה Mishnah
has has all these things that are ממון המזיק *mamon hamazik*: שן
shen *shein*, רגל regel, *regel*, בור *bor*, and אש eish. *esh*, and
has excluded אדם Adam. *adam* and excluded קרן keren. *keren*. So it's
a very tight coherent משנה Mishna, *mishna* that it's only things that
are ממון המזיק *mamon hamazik* and only things that are מועד mu'ad.
*muad* from the very beginning. And by the way, that allows a
conceptual possibility that קרן keren. *keren* is like חייב chayav, *chayav* at
a different type of a way, because remember, קרן keren *keren* is
only half, it might be קנס *knas*, there might not be so
much negligence by קרן keren, *keren*. So conceptually, קרן keren, *keren* and
אדם Adam *adam* could be very distinct categories from the four in
the משנה Mishna *mishna* according to שמואל Shmuel. *Shmuel*. Now we're going
to go back and look at רב Rav, *Rav*. ושמואל מאי טעמא
לא אמר כרב *v'shmuel mai ta'ama lo amar k'rav*? Why what so
what was the that was שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel* had to defend his
read if you know why doesn't שור shor *shor* all aspects of
שור shor *shor*? And he explains שור shor, *shor* is רגל *regel*
and מבעה maveh *mav'eh* is שן *shein*. Now רב Rav *Rav* who
said שור shor *shor* means all שור shor *shor*: קרן keren *keren*,
שן *shein*, and רגל *regel*, what's the weakness of his read in
the משנה Mishna. *mishna*? ושמואל מאי טעמא לא אמר כרב *v'shmuel mai
ta'ama lo amar k'rav*? אמר לך אי סלקא דעתך אדם Adam, *amar
lach i salka da'atach adam*, if you think that מבעה maveh *mav'eh*
means a human, הא קתני סיפא *ha'ketani seifa*: שור shor המועד ושור
המזיק ברשות הניזק והאדם *shor hamuad v'shor hamazik b'reshut hanizak v'ha'adam*. There's
a later משנה Mishna, *mishna* that lists the things that are that
you always pay full amount, and it says a שור shor המועד
*shor hamuad* like if a if there's קרן keren, *keren* if it's
קרן keren *keren* but it's been warned three times, or if it
does it in the owner's domain, in the domain of the damaged
not of the person who's your ox comes into my domain and
gores my ox. So you have to pay full even if it's
only the first time because it happened in my domain. We'll see
about that later. And the human being, all these people pay you
know full amounts. So we get to אדם Adam *adam*, so so
שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel* says we're going to say אדם Adam, *adam* later,
so I don't want to think that אדם Adam *adam* is up
here in the first משנה Mishna *mishna*. ולתני ברישא *v'lisni b'reisha*. So
now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says okay I get you שמואל Shmuel,
*Shmuel* that you're saying אדם Adam. *adam* was down there and you
didn't want to say it up here in the earlier משנה Mishnah,
*mishna*, or you didn't have to say it appeared in the earlier
משנה Mishnah. *mishna*, but why didn't it appear in the earlier משנה
Mishnah *mishna*? You know, it is one of the things you're חייב
chayav. *chayav* for. So he says very logically: בנזקי ממון קמיירי בנזקי
גופו לא קמיירי *b'nizkei mamon kamayri b'nizkei gufo lo kamayri*. Okay, because
no, the משנה Mishnah. *mishna* is saying you know things that are
your property that damage, not when you yourself damage. You personally damage,
that's a conceptual different category. So שמואל Shmuel, *Shmuel* is making a
very nice argument: I do not want to say אדם Adam *adam*,
we're going to get to אדם Adam, *adam* later, but the אדם
Adam *adam* is conceptually different from the cases in the משנה Mishnah
*mishna*. ורב נמי הא קתני אדם Adam, בסיפא *v'rav nami ha'katani adam
b'seifa*? But for רב Rav *Rav*, you know, why would we try
to read אדם Adam, *adam* above, doesn't אדם Adam. *adam* appear later?
אמר לך רב Rav, הוא למשוי בהדי מועד muad, אדם Adam. הוא
דאתא *amar lach Rav hu l'mishvei bahadi mu'ad adam hu d'asa*. No,
when it says אדם Adam, *adam* later, it's not coming to introduce
אדם Adam, *adam* as something you're חייב chayav *chayav* for, it's coming
it's at a separate משנה Mishnah *mishna* that says here are things
that you always pay full amount from the very get-go, okay? But
it's not coming to newly introduce a category. And yes, אדם Adam,
*adam* appeared above beginning in the list of אבות avos נזיקין *avos
nezikin*, it's one of the אבות avos נזיקין *avos nezikin*, and it'll
be restated later when we list things that you're חייב chayav *chayav*
fully. That's a very simple answer. The real point is is שמואל
Shmuel, *Shmuel's* question that אדם Adam, *adam* is conceptually different. So let's
take a look. ומאי לא הרי הכי קאמר *u'mai lo harei hachi
ka'amar*? Now, here how what do you do with the לא הרי
*lo harei*, right? This is I mentioned this earlier, right? This is
like it's easier for שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel* to think about the strength
of שן *shein* versus the strength of קרן Keren *keren* or versus
the strength of רגל *regel*, each one has its own unique strength.
But אדם Adam, *adam* you would think you're like always חייב chayav
*chayav* for, so what's the you know what's the what's the reason
that if the תורה *Torah* just told me שור *shor*, I would
not have been able to know that you're חייב chayav. *chayav* for
אדם Adam *adam*? הכי קאמר *hachi ka'amar*, here's what it says: לא
ראי השור שמשלם את הכופר כראי אדם Adam. שאין משלם את הכופר
*lo re'i hashor she'meshalem es hakoper k're'i adam she'ein meshalem es hakoper*.
There's one way in which שור *shor* is חייב *chayav* for more
than you're חייב *chayav* by אדם Adam *adam*. Right so maybe they're
about its characteristics, before we're talking about its characteristics: כוונתו להזיק *kavanaso
l'hazik*, הנאה להיזקו *hana'a l'hezeku*,
okay, maybe in terms of maybe there there's nothing that's stronger about
a שור *shor* than about a human being, but but there is
something about the demands the תורה *Torah* makes. When an animal gores
a human being, if it has done it three times, if it's
a מועד *muad*, then it's then it's going to pay and it
kills the person, it pays כופר *koper*, it pays a type of
אם כופר יושת עליו *im koper yushas alav*, an atonement payment. That
never exists by a human who kills a human being. A human
kills a human being, whether intentionally or unintentionally, that's always dealt with
as a case of murder or manslaughter. The concept that there should
be a payment for that is fundamentally like excluded from that case.
There's no concept of כופר *koper*. So therefore, that you could say
because it's weightier there's no concept of כופר *koper*. כופר *koper* is
a sort of is an atonement and gets you off of the
weighty sense that this life was destroyed because of your animal, so
you pay a כופר *koper* for it, whereas by human being there's
no כופר *koper* because you have to either get executed or go
into גלות *galus* or whatever the case might be. But nevertheless, the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says it's a way in which שור *shor* is
weightier, at least the payments of שור *shor* exist in a way
that it doesn't for אדם Adam. *adam*. So if the תורה *Torah*
just said that a שור *shor* you're חייב *chayav*, I wouldn't have
known you're חייב *chayav* for an אדם adam *adam* for damages because
there's ways in which the תורה makes greater demands on payments for
a שור than it does on an
אדם. Adam, לא ראי שור משום דכופר כראי אדם שאין שם כופר
ולא אדם שחייב בארבעה דברים Lo re'i shor mishum d'kopher k'orei Adam
she'ein sham kopher v'lo Adam she'chayav b'arbah devarim and while we're talking
about about about payments rather than about characteristics, you know, if it
had said that אדם Adam is חייב, I wouldn't have known that
שור is חייב. I mean, number one in terms of characteristics, אדם,
Adam you did it yourself, but again, we're focusing here on payments.
So you want to talk about payments, fine. By a human who
who who wounds another human, you pay not only the
damage, נזק, nezek, but you pay צער, tza'ar, ריפוי, ripuy, שבת, sheves,
בושת, boshes, you pay for, you know, the the doctor's bills and
the embarrassment and the pain and the loss of work. So therefore
there are ways in which payments of when a human does the
damage to another human is more weighty than when an ox does
it. כראי השור שאין בו ארבעה דברים. K'orei hashor she'ein bo arbah
devarim. Okay, so if it had just said one, I wouldn't have
known the other because each one has a type of a payment
that doesn't exist by the other, so I could have assumed that
because you're חייב by one you're חייב by the other, so it
had to say both.
הצד השוה שבהן שדרכן להזיק. Hatzad hashaveh shebahen shedarkan lehazzik. Okay, that
they've they have a propensity to damage
now, and, you know, ושמירתן עליך u'shmiratan alecha etc., etc. So that's
how we're now reading the משנה, Mishnah but we've introduced אדם Adam
and they both have רוח חיים ruach chayim and that's the opening
of the משנה Mishnah and they're דרכן להזיק. darkan lehazzik. But now
the גמרא Gemara. says a very important question. וכי שור דרכו להזיק?
V'chi shor darko lehazzik? Is שור, it's way to damage? Now presumably
it's asking this because of the קרן. Keren Remember for רב, Rav
שור is
קרן. Keren שאינו רגל She'eino regel for שמואל. Shmuel שמואל managed to
get קרן Keren in not in the משנה. Mishnah Okay, but for
רב Rav that it's קרן, Keren you know, that's not דרכו להזיק,
darko lehazzik, that's unusual the first three times, it's why you only
pay half. So the גמרא Gemara says במועד. B'mu'ad. Okay, but yes,
when it's been warned three times, now now it's clear that it's
developed this propensity.
ומועד דרכו להזיק? U'mu'ad darko lehazzik? Which is a an amazing question
of the גמרא. Gemara You know, even if it's done it three
times, still for an animal to gore is a very unusual thing,
it's not דרכו להזיק. darko lehazzik. the גמרא Gemara is now assuming
that maybe if it did it three times, maybe you the owner
have greater negligence or you know maybe I don't know it's something
we gotta make you pay you know despite the fact that it's
unusual but somehow it's assuming that doing it three times does not
yet mean that it's a normal thing, that it's דרכו להזיק. darko
lehazzik. So the גמרא Gemara says yes, כיון דאייעד אורחיה הוא. keivan
d'ai'ad orchei hu. Once it's been warned and it's happened three times,
that's normal. So now we're really seeing what's so nice about שמואל's
read. By excluding אדם, Adam that's conceptually different. And by based on
רב's Rav read of שמואל, not רב, Rav רבא's Rava read of
שמואל, that we're excluding קרן, keren it means קרן might be a
completely different category. It's not דרכו להזיק, darko lehazzik, maybe there's not
so much negligence, even if you pay full maybe it's not דרכו
להזיק darko lehazzik the גמרא Gemara thinks the possibility. So for שמואל,
he's able to say they're very different categories. There's the classic things
that are דרכו להזיק, darkan lehazzik, then there's קרן, then there's אדם
Adam. when you do it yourself. רב Rav, puts everything in the
משנה, Mishnah which means A, we have to look at קרן as
דרכו להזיק, darko lehazzik, at least by the time it's a מועד.
But now we have to also discuss אדם. Adam Is אדם Adam
conceptually the same obligation as when your ox goes out, as when
you yourself damage? So let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this, אדם דרכו להזיק? Adam darko lehazzik? And is a
person, are you normally go around and do damage like, you know,
your animals if you don't watch them, they'll go and they'll eat
other people's food or whatever, but human beings don't normally go about
and create damage. So the גמרא Gemara says בישן. B'yashen. Yes, if
he's sleeping. So if you're sleeping, you'll bang into things. ישן דרכו
להזיק? Yashen darko lehazzik? So the גמרא Gemara still questions that. Really?
Is that really normal? So the גמרא Gemara says yes, כיון דכייף
ופשיט אורחיה הוא. keivan d'kaif u'pashit orchei hu. Yes, if when you're
stretching out and you're moving around in your sleep, you can bang
things, you know, you're so so yes, there is a propensity to
do damage when you're asleep. All right. So now the גמרא Gemara
says ושמירתן עליך. u'shmiratan alecha. So now but the גמרא Gemara doesn't
the משנה Mishnah, doesn't say דרכו להזיק. darko lehazzik. The next phrase
that characterizes it is
ושמירתן עליך. u'shmiratan alecha. ושמירתן עליך, u'shmiratan alecha, אדם שמירת גופו עליו.
Adam shmirat gufo alav. the גמרא Gemara says what do you mean?
It's not like you know, it's not like it's something else that
you have a responsibility to watch. ושמירתן עליך u'shmiratan alecha means it's
something separate from you that you have a responsibility to watch. If
you're talking about a human being, it should have said you have
your responsibility to watch yourself. So that should have been the phrase,
not ושמירתן עליך, u'shmiratan alecha, it should have been שמירת גופו עליו,
shmirat gufo alav, you're responsible to yourself. So the גמרא Gemara says
okay, ולטעמיך הא דתני קרנא, u'l'ta'amecha ha d'tani Karna, but wait a
minute, we've got a ברייתא Braisa that קרנא Karna teaches, that ארבע
אבות נזיקין ואדם אחד מהן arbah avot nezikin v'Adam echad mehen says
ארבע אבות נזיקין arbah avos nezikin and explicitly lists אדם, Adam and
he says, and אדם שמירת גופו עליו, v'Adam shmirat gufo alav, and
the same, and the same question could be asked, what does it
mean ושמירתן עליך? u'shmiratan alecha? So you're blaming me says
רב Rav that
I assume
But like רבי אבהו Rabbi Abahu taught that תנא Tanna who taught
אדם in the משנה, Mishnah he says when you get to אדם,
don't describe it as שמירתן עליך, shemirosan alecha, their watching them is
on you, meaning that the thing is separate from you. When you
talk about אדם, you should say your watching your own self is
your responsibility. That's how you should articulate what it is by an
אדם. Top of ד עמוד ב. dalet amud beis. So הכא נמי
אדם שמירות גופו עליו. hacha nami adam shemiros gufo alav. So we'll
say the same here in our משנה. Yes, our משנה when it
says the צד השווה שבהן, tzad hashava shebahen, it says שמירתן עליך,
shemirosan alecha,
but that's a phrase that works by everything other than אדם. אדם,
if we were to describe אדם, we would say you're responsible for
yourself. So it's true, the phrase doesn't exactly describe אדם, it describes
the other things that are separate from you, and by אדם, if
we're talking about אדם, we would tweak the phrase to mean you're
responsible for yourself. Okay, but the really important thing here to appreciate
is, besides the question of technically the phrase, is that שמואל has
allowed for קרן to not be about the classic דרכו להזיק darko
lehazik and the negligence around דרכו להזיק. darko lehazik. קרן could be
its own path and אדם certainly could be its own path. There
could be a fundamental sense, you break it, you pay for it,
it's not because you were negligent for watching yourself, right? So that
phrase דרכו להזיק darko lehazik and ממונך, mamoncha, your property, by the
way תוספות Tosafot points out the גמרא Gemara doesn't ask ממונך mamoncha
here, which gets to the question of is the word ממונך mamoncha
in the משנה. So that conceptual basis that the reason you're חייב
is A, it's your property, B, you have a responsibility to watch
it, you were negligent with that responsibility and therefore you pay. שמואל
says I'm happy with that if we take off קרן and אדם.
Those might be different tracks. Okay, you know, קרן is your ממונך
mamoncha but it might not be דרכו להזיק, darko lehazik, it might
be a different track. And אדם is certainly different. For רב who
puts them in, he both has to say that קרן works in
the same type of דרכו להזיק, darko lehazik, at least when it
becomes a מועד, and for the human being, that's particularly shocking. It's
not like you did it, you broke it, you paid for it,
it's like you are responsible to watch yourself, and if you didn't
watch yourself, you have to pay because you were negligent with your
responsibility. You know, similar to if you didn't watch your animal. And
it's very strange to be putting those all together. That's what comes
through רב's read of מבעה maveh being אדם. Okay, now the גמרא
Gemara says like this. So now we're just going to have some
other possibilities of what the word מבעה maveh. might mean. מתקיף לה
רב מרי. maskif lah Rav Mari. רב מרי Rav Mari asks, ואימא
מבעה זה המים. v'eima maveh zeh hamayim. Why not say מבעה maveh
means water? כדכתיב כקדוח אש המסים מים תבעה אש, kedichsiv kichtoch eish
hamasim mayim tivei eish, like the same way the, you know, the
fire will burn and whatever, you know, cause things to melt, water
will also bubble, could be bubbled by the fire, put out the
fire and cause the water to boil. So the גמרא Gemara, says,
מי כתיב מים נבעו? mi ksiv mayim nivu? So the גמרא Gemara
says no, because the word תבעה tivei there, like which means like
בועות, ba'buos, which actually you know means like bubbles or whatever, it's
not the water is bubbling the fire, מים mayim is plural, it
would be מים נבעו. mayim nivu. תבעה אש כתיב. tivei eish ksiv.
The fire is causing the water to bubble. So the water wouldn't
be a מבעה. maveh מתקיף לה רב זביד. maskif lah Rav Zvid.
ואימא מבעה זה האש. v'eima maveh zeh haeish. Well let's say מבעה
maveh means fire. Fine, so then it would mean the fire is
bubbling the water. Let's say it means fire. דכתיב תבעה באש, dechsiv
tivei ba'eish, the תבעה tivei goes by the fire. אי הכי, ei
hachi, says the גמרא, Gemara מאי המבעה וההבער? mai hamaveh vehahaver? No,
you can't say that because הבער haver means fire. So מבעה maveh
is something else. וכי תימא פירושא קמפרש, vechi teima perusha kamfaresh, and
if you're saying it's explaining, מבעה maveh i.e. הבער. haver. אי הכי
ארבעה? ei hachi arba? Then it wouldn't be four, תלתא הוו. tlata
havu. You would be conflating מבעה maveh and הבער. haver. וכי תימא
תנא שור דאית ביה
תרתי? vechi teima tana shor d'is bei tarti? No, שור maybe includes
two things, maybe שור is I don't know, שן and רגל, and
מבעה maveh and הבער haver are one thing which is אש. eish
So the גמרא says, אי הכי לא זה וזה שיש בהן רוח
חיים, ei hachi lo zeh vezeh sheyeish bahen ruach chayim, אש מאי
רוח חיים אית ביה? eish mai ruach chayim is bei?
But remember the משנה said compared מבעה maveh and שור and said
that both of them are alive, but אש eish, isn't alive. ותו
מאי קרי לאש? v'su mai karei l'eish? And then it says neither
of these are like אש, eish so clearly מבעה maveh and אש
eish are different things. I mean, excuse me, yeah, מבעה and אש
are different things. Okay, now we are done with מבעה and הבער
haver and really it's been a very great first three דף daf
of conceptually what are the categories, where do they come from, what
are their characteristics, and whether conceptually קרן and אדם should be seen
of in the same category as the others. Okay, now we're going
to have ברייתא, braisa, a ברייתא braisa that add to the list
of four. תני רבי אושעיה, tani Rabbi Oshaya, רבי אושעיה Rabbi Oshaya
taught in a ברייתא, braisa, שלש עשרה אבות נזיקין, shelosh esreh avos
nezikin, 13, and we're going to discuss tomorrow's דף daf what the
אבות means, not that they have תולדות, tolados, אבות is going to
be for a different הלכה halacha which we'll discuss tomorrow.
What
are the
13? שומר חנם והשואל נושא שכר והשוכר, shomer chinam vehashoel nosei sachar
vehasocher, so he's including all the שומרים shomrim that when they're negligent
they have to pay or when they, you know, or if it
got, you know, under certain
circumstances. Sometimes even without negligence; by a שואל sho'el *sho'el* even accidents
you pay for, by a שומר שכר *shomer sachar* and a שוכר
*socher*, somebody who is paid to watch or somebody who rents something
they pay for גניבה ואבידה *gneiva v'aveida* even if it's stolen or
lost but they don't pay if it's a complete accident. Okay, so
those are four. שומר חינם *shomer chinam*, the one who watches for
free who pays under all circumstances, השואל *hasho'el* the one who borrows,
excuse me שומר חינם *shomer chinam* excuse me one who watches for
free who only pays for negligence, שואל *sho'el* is a borrower who
pays for all circumstances even for accidents, נושא שכר והשוכר *nose sachar
v'hasocher*, נושא שכר *nose sachar* is the one that is paid to
watch, השוכר *hasocher* somebody who rents and those cases they pay for
even, you know, small negligence like גניבה ואבידה *gneiva v'aveida* but they
do not pay for full accident. That's four. צער וריפוי שבת ובושת
*tzar v'ripoi sheves u'boshes* and if a human wounds another human in
addition to paying נזק nezek *nezek* which is אדם המזיק Adam ha-mazik?
*adam hamazik* you also going to pay צער *tzar* pain that's suffered,
ריפוי *ripoi* the healing, שבת *sheves* the work that you were kept
out of and בושת *boshes* the embarrassment, so we're now up to
eight. Okay, וארבע... sorry נזק *nezek* I should have skipped first, נזק
צער וריפוי שבת ובושת *nezek tzar v'ripoi sheves u'boshes*. Okay, starts with
the נזק *nezek* the damages because the משנה *mishna* might not include
אדם *adam* like רב *rav* you know like שמואל *shmuel* and even
if it includes אדם *adam* like רב *rav* that's when a human
damages property but if a human damages another human the idea of
paying נזק *nezek* for the damages for the wounds that itself is
a separate category. So we've added nine to the משנה *mishna*, the
four שומרים shomrim? *shomrim* and the five payments that you make for
wounding another person. Okay, that's nine plus the four in the משנה
*mishna* and again just to say if משנה *mishna* included אדם *adam*
that was אדם *adam* that damaged property a person that damages a
person we're going to include the, you know, that's a separate category
and that has all those five payments. וארבע דמתניתין הא תלת סרי
*v'arba d'masnisan ha tlesrei* that's thirteen. ותני דידן מאי טעמא לא תני
הני *v'tani didan mai taama lo tani hani* why did our תנא
*tanna* not list these? בשלמא לשמואל בניזקי ממון קמיירי בניזקי גופא לא
קמיירי *b'shlama l'shmuel binizkei mamon qama'ei binizkei gufa lo qama'ei* according to
שמואל *shmuel* it's very easy all of these are things that a
human being is responsible for either for damaging directly wounding another human
being or for being negligent with property that is and we're not
talking about humans we're talking about when your property damages. אלא לרב
ליתני *ela l'rav lisni* why according to רב *rav* why did our
משנה *mishna* not include these? תנא אדם בכל מילי דאדם *tanna adam
b'chol milei d'adam* because it says אדם *adam* which includes all things
humans can do including the שומרים shomrim *shomrim* and including damaging another
person. לרבי יאשיה נמי הא תנא ליה אדם *l'rabbi yoshia nami ha
tanna lei adam* okay according to רבי יאשיה *rabbi yoshia* how would
רב *rav* explain רבי יאשיה *rabbi yoshia* because רבי יאשיה *rabbi yoshia*
is a תנא *tanna* so how would רב *rav* explain why if
the משנה *mishna* said אדם *adam* why did רבי יאשיה *rabbi yoshia*
feel it necessary to add these other categories weren't they included in
the אדם *adam* of the משנה *mishna*? תרי גווני אדם *t'rei gavnei
adam*
there are two types of אדם *adam* תנא אדם דאזיק אדם ותנא
אדם דאזיק שור *tanna adam d'azik adam v'tanna adam d'azik shor* okay
so first we're discussing the, you know, the second part about which
is what I was saying before about wounding yes the משנה *mishna*
talks about אדם המזיק *adam hamazik* when a person damages property but
there's a totally different category it's the eighth פרק *perek* of this
מסכתא החובל *masechta hachovel* when a person damages another person and wounds
them that's חבלה chavalah, *chabala* that's, you know, wounding, okay, and that
has five payments not just one payment of damage and therefore the
משנה *mishna* is limited to the, you know, humans damaging property not
humans damaging humans that should be said explicitly separately. That's four. אי
הכי *i hachi* says the גמרא *gemara* שור נמי ליתני תרי גווני
שור ליתני שור דאזיק שור וליתני שור דאזיק אדם *shor nami lisni
t'rei gavnei shor lisni shor d'azik shor v'lisni shor d'azik adam* if
we're going to distinguish, you know, when the object is damaged is
the thing being damaged a property you know a physical like just
a material object or is it a human being and therefore we're
going to list separately in the ברייתא Baraita *brayta* when a human
damages another human so why not list separately in the ברייתא *brayta*
when an ox damages another human right if the משנה *mishna* is
limited to when property is damaged why not have another case of
an ox that damages a human? האי מאי *hai mai* says the
גמרא *gemara* what type of question is that בשלמא אדם דאזיק שור
נזק הוא דמשלם אדם דאזיק אדם משלם ארבעה דברים *b'shlama adam d'azik
shor nezek hu d'mishalem adam d'azik adam mishalem arba devarim* גמרא *gemara*
says no no no it's not just a technical question of is
it property or person it's whether it really creates a different halachic
category when a human damages a property that's considered מזיק mazik, *mazik*
you know damaging property and therefore that's our משנה *mishna* when a
human damages another human that's called חבלה chavalah, *chabala* wounding and that
has a whole separate category of payment you pay five things damages
plus four others okay and therefore we're going to list it separately
it doesn't just happen to be different it's a completely different category.
אלא שור מאי לי שור דאזיק שור מאי לי שור דאזיק אדם
האי והאי נזק הוא דמשלם *ela shor mai li shor d'azik shor
mai li שור דאזיק אדם האי והאי נזק הוא דמשלם* but when
an ox gores even if it gores a human even though, true,
there will be... Pain and suffering and being out of work and
doctor's bills and all of that, but halachically it's treated as property.
Halachically you just look at what was the damage and you pay
the damage and it's not conceptualized differently than an ox goring property.
So, therefore, the משנה says when it says ox for רב, it
means whether an ox gores property or gores humans, it's all conceptually
the same. You just look at it in terms of damages, but
when it says אדם, רבי אושעיא Rebbe Oshaya is going to say
that אדם in the משנה is the אדם that pays just damages
when it damages property, the same way the ox always pays just
damages. Everything in the משנה is when only thing is being paid
is damages. So it's ox goring property or people and the human
destroying property. But we're going to list separately in the ברייתא human
damaging a human, that's חבלה, that's when there's a whole other range
of payment. Okay, so now the גמרא says one minute, so fine.
The משנה is limited to cases when it talks about person of
a person damaging property. So why did רבי אושעיא Rebbe Oshaya also
have to list the
ארבעה שומרים? arba'ah shomrim? והשומר חנם והשואל נושא שכר והשוכר דאדם דאזיק
שור הוא וקתני? V'hashomer chinam v'hasho'el nosay sachar v'hasocher d'Adam d'azik shor
hu u-ktani? So then why list the four שומרים? shomrim, The four
שומרים shomrim, aren't cases of a person damaging
property, are cases of a person damaging property. So shouldn't that have
already been included in the case in the משנה where it talks
about an אדם המזיק? So it says תני היזק דבידיים ותני היזק
דממילא. tani hezek d'beyadayim v'tani hezek d'mmeila. No, there's a big difference.
The משנה is talking about a classic case of מזיק, mazik? right?
That's why I assume that when I read the four שומרים, shomrim.
probably you were saying what is that doing in the list? That's
not a case of damage, that's negligence and something else causes a
damage and you're responsible. So that's what it's saying. Even for רב
that אדם is listed in the משנה, רבי אושעיא Rebbe Oshaya needed
to list his because in the משנה we're talking about a person
that damages directly, does an act of damaging property. רבי אושעיא Rebbe
Oshaya says I want to point out that, you know, you could
say אדם represents everything, but I want to point out that there
are conceptually other categories of אדם.
There's
an אדם who damages a human being, that's called חבלה, that has
these all these special payments. And there's also an אדם that allows
property, is negligent in the damage of property, and that's also going
to be, like, that's the case of שומרים, shomrim and that's also
going to be places where you're going to be חייב. Now the
thing that should be noted is that in that case of ממילא,
m'meila, are we conceptualizing it as, you know, a מזיק? mazik? I
mean, you know, ארבעה אבות נזיקין. arba'ah avot nezikin. I mean, in
a way, the from the perspective of the person who lost their
property, it was a damage. My property was destroyed, and I want
compensation, and maybe that's all we mean to say here: ways in
which, you know, as an אדם you have to go ahead and
pay because נזק occurred. But, but you know, do we conceptualize it
that if you were negligent, same way if I'm negligent with my
ox and it gores you, we conceptualize it like I damaged you
or my property did an act of damage. If I'm negligent watching
your, you know, you gave me your phone to watch and then
something happened and it broke, is it like because my negligence allowed
that to happen was it like I broke it? Now you might
be able to say that by פשיעה, peshiah, real negligence. Would you
say it by if it got stolen, you know, and so on
and my negligence was minor? Would you say it even by a
שואל who wasn't who even in a case of a total accident
that we view it like he was the מזיק? So that's not
so clear. That's a very important question by שומרים. When שומרים pay,
is it because we conceptualize them as having been negligent and having
done the act of damage and that's why it would be listed
in the מזיקים, mazikim, you know, in in this in this list
according to רבי אושעיא, Rebbe Oshaya, or are we just saying that,
you know, that no, these are cases of damage property that was
damaged and who has to pay? And that might be sort of
what you know more what we are saying.
Okay, we will see about more of this tomorrow.